<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods blessing in blasting, and his mercy in mildew Tvvo sermons sutable to these times of dearth: by Iames Rowlandson B. in D. and pastor at East-Tysted in Hampshire.</title>
            <author>Rowlandson, James, 1576 or 7-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116262</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851479</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851479</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11144)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1218:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods blessing in blasting, and his mercy in mildew Tvvo sermons sutable to these times of dearth: by Iames Rowlandson B. in D. and pastor at East-Tysted in Hampshire.</title>
                  <author>Rowlandson, James, 1576 or 7-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 73, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland for William Bladen, at the great north doore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16753:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16753:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GODS BLESSING IN BLASTING, AND HIS MERCY IN MILDEW.</p>
            <p>TWO SERMONS SVTABLE TO THESE times of Dearth: By IAMES ROWLANDSON <hi>B. in D. and Paſtor</hi> at EAST-TYSTED in Hampſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ESAY 30.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Though the Lord giue you the bread of aduerſitie, and the water of affliction, yet ſhall not thy Teachers be remoued into a corner any more; but thine eyes ſhall ſee thy Teachers.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Haviland</hi> for <hi>William Bladen,</hi> at the great North doore of PAVLS. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16753:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16753:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORTHIEST GENTLE-WOMAN, AND MOST vertuous Matron, M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> ANNE BILSON, the true widow of that famous and moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Prelate, my L. BILSON, late Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and one of his Maieſties moſt honourable Priuie Counſell, my ſometimes moſt louing <hi>Patron,</hi> and thrice ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Lord: all the graces of Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in this world, and the glories of it in another.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot more abhor flatterie, than your ſelfe will flie at the very ſhadow of it; as <hi>Moſes</hi> at the ſight of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. But giue not backe, it is no ſuch terrible obiect, which here I offer to your eies. It is but a rod, and that a gracious one, <hi>Gods bleſſing to our Nation euen in Blaſting, and his mercy in Mildew.</hi> This I haue ſomewhat ouer-boldly aduentured to caſt in your way before ye were aware of it. But you know to take it vp by the
<pb facs="tcp:16753:3"/>
true end, which it to teſtifie mine vnfained reuerence and reſpect, both to your ſelfe, and to the memorie of that moſt honourable man, that is gone before vs into his <hi>Maſters ioy.</hi> I could not ſatisfie my ſelfe, if in the dedication of theſe my firſt labours of this kinde, I did not charge them, in the firſt place to viſit that Familie, to which (as Gods inſtrument) I muſt referre the greateſt part of my worldly encouragements, or vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dergoe the cenſure of <hi>the nine that returned not with thankes. Two poore mites</hi> theſe are, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which neither the <hi>Lords treaſurie,</hi> nor your ſelfe haue any ſuch need, but that they might well be ſpared; yet he that accepted <hi>the Widowes,</hi> giues me hope that neither he, nor the Widow will reiect mine. I ſpeak not this in confidence of their worth (for ſlender they muſt needs be, that are ſpunne moſt out of mine owne meditations) but in regard of his goodneſſe, that hath giuen you yours, and by his mercifull acceptation of our ſmalleſt endeuours done in truth, teacheth vs not to deſpiſe one onothers ſeruices, or offices of loue. That Ocean of his neuer exhauſted bounty, likes it well, that to his glorie we ſhould refund whatſoeuer good we haue receiued by his grace, be it leſſe or more. The ſmalleſt drops of ſuch raine when they fall into that ſea, finde no leſſe welcome, than the deeplieſt charged riuers. You deſire (I know) to imitate the heauenly
<pb facs="tcp:16753:3"/>
Father, of whom we muſt all be followers, if we will be approued children; and euen in this. Therefore I feare not to preſent you with this ſmall paper-retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution. It is all and the firſt gift that euer I tendred, either to your ſelfe or to any other: a poore one (God wot) yet a demonſtration of my thankfulneſſe. Gold and Siluer I had none, or had I offered for your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours and my Lords, either before or after that I felt them, I am perſwaded that the repulſe would haue beene ſhamefull,<note place="margin">Acts 8.20.</note> and that too with <hi>S. Peters</hi> deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now alſo euen this my teſtimonie of your goodnes towards me, is more (as little as it is) than you expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, than you deſired: ſo abundantly doe you content your ſelfe in the ſole ſecrecie of doing well. And yet me thinkes, it is pittie that vertue ſhould be ſo modeſt as to loue obſcurity, vnwilling to haue it ſelfe knowne, when vice is growne ſo impudent, as not to feare the light. If painted viſages (viſards rather) dare bazard the cenſure of a publique view, ſhould natiue beauty bluſh to ſhew its face? Yet your retiredneſſe is commendable, but your contentedneſſe with it, much more: in that hauing liued ſometimes in the open eie of the world ſo worthily, you can now thus cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuote your ſelfe (as it were) to a more priuate, not leſſe pious courſe of life:<note place="margin">Heb. 13 4. 1 Tim. 5.3.</note> your former condition was <hi>honourable amongſt all men;</hi> and none (ſaue
<pb facs="tcp:16753:4"/>
they that either know not the Apoſtles precept, or your ſelfe) but will ſay that your preſent is as much to <hi>be honoured.</hi> The ancient of daies giue you ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of many, and happie yeeres, with the abundance of his bleſsings, that you may continue to be (as you are) a gratious preſident of pietie and grauitie to your ſex; a long liu'd mother in Iſrael; the great comfort of your vertuous children; of whom you may ſay more truly than <hi>Cornelia</hi> of her <hi>Gracchi, Haec ſunt ornamenta mea,</hi> Theſe are my Iewels, theſe my abilements: Such be they long to your comfort, ſtill to Gods glory, whoſe vnerring ſpirit of truth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct you and them, with vs all, through this wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne, to our promiſed Canaan. And ſo I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Seruant in</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>IAMES ROVVLANDSON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16753:4"/>
            <head>GODS BLESSING IN BLASTING, AND his mercy in Mildew. THE FIRST SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HAGGAI 2.17.</hi>
                  </bibl> I ſmote you with blaſting, and with mildew, and with haile, in all the labours of your bands; yet yee turned not to me, ſaith the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wice I finde this Text in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and in the ſame words almoſt; here and in the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> chap. 4. verſ. 9.<note place="margin">Amos 4.9.</note> Here they mention a correction vpon the <hi>Iewes</hi> after their returne from Captiuitie; there, a iudgement vpon the reuolted <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> or the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16753:5"/>
ten Tribes. Here the <hi>Iewes</hi> were thus afflicted for not building Gods houſe; there the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for ſchiſmatically leauing the worſhip of God houſe.</p>
            <p>Hence thus inferre by the way, if you pleaſe: It can be no leſſe fault to abandon the Church than not to build it: Nor deſerues it a leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> affliction, not to repaire to the Temple, than not to repaire it. Vnderſtand it thus: He that obſtinately refuſeth to come to the Church (be he a recuſant Papiſt, or Schiſmaticke) offends no leſſe, if not more, than the churle or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer that holds his hand from contributing to it when there is need. For the buildings and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terials of the Temple are but the body of it, but the ſoule of the Temple is Gods ſeruice in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And ſurely were not the couetous man an Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>later, as well as the Recuſant, I ſhould leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blame him for ſhutting vp his purſe, than other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for cutting off their perſons, from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But it is hard to ſay whether is the worſe; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Both ſo bad, that there is no great choiſe.</p>
            <p>Yet the <hi>Iewes</hi> here in my text, though beaten with the ſame rods of Blaſting and Mildew, wherewith the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were ſmitten in <hi>Amos,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16753:5"/>
ſinned not after the like manner. The Tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple was yet ſtanding, when <hi>Amos</hi> propheſied to the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> which happened in the daies of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the latter,<note place="margin">Amos 1.1.</note> the ſonne of <hi>Ioaſh</hi> the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> two hundred forty ſix yeeres before the deſolation of it by the <hi>Aſsyrians,</hi> or thereabout. So the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> forſooke not the Temple for the ruines of it, but for the rent which <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nebat</hi> had made from the houſe of <hi>Dauid;</hi> from which time they were turned Idolaters, and <hi>turned the glory of God into the ſimilitude of a calfe that eateth haye.</hi> Acceſſe was not denied them, either to <hi>Dauids</hi> throne for iuſtice, or to the Temple for deuotion; but becauſe they had broken from the houſe of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 12.6. Iohn 4.20.</note> they would breake from Gods houſe too. And whereas the Lord had commanded them for publique worſhip to reſort to the Temple, they left <hi>the place which he had choſen,</hi> and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their maſter Pilot, <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> (whoſe policy ſteered all their piety towards the landing of himſelfe at a kingdome) carried all their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices to <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel;</hi> and ſo became more brutiſh in their ſeruice, than the Idoll-calues which they ſerued. But for the <hi>Iewes</hi> now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from captiuity, let them be thus farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16753:6"/>
If they frequented not the Temple, they could not, it being not yet reedified: If they builded it not againe, they had this to ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or themſelues, that they had begunne to doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, but were reſtrained by the letters of <hi>Arta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerxes,</hi> procured by the malicious ſuggeſtion, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the inſtigation of their bad neighbours; and ſo were forced to deſiſt from the worke till the ſecond yeere of <hi>Darius</hi> king of <hi>Perſia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>Ezra.</hi> 4. verſ. 24. Yet though thus wee might plead for them, or they for themſelues, all this will not proue them blameleſſe: Excuſe them it may <hi>à tanto, non à toto;</hi> It is too narrow a cloake to couer all their nakedneſſe, for herein it leaues them bare, and open to Gods ſmitings: for being once enioyned this taske by God himſelfe, and hauing put their hands vnto it, they ſhould not haue giuen it ouer for any dread of man. Now, that they were ſet about this worke by the Lord himſelfe,<note place="margin">Ezra 1.5.</note> is plaine, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 1.5. Where it is ſaid, <hi>that he raiſed vp their ſpirits to build the Temple:</hi> to wit, he ſtirred vp theirs, by his ſpirit, the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof they ſhould haue held as a mandat, or equiualent to an expreſſe command. Whence theſe concluſions reſult, which we will but a little more than mention.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16753:6"/>1. That the ſacred ſuggeſtions of Gods ſpirit in ſtirring vp our ſpirits to doe his will, would be hearkned vnto, and obeyed with conſtancie. For being diuine dictates, though ſecretly inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they haue an equipollency or equall weight with the plaineſt precepts. But how theſe are diſtinguiſhable from diabolicall deluſions, or concupiſcentiall phantaſies of men, I haue ſhewed more largely at another time: onely now receiue this ſhort direction; Whatſoeuer motion would tranſport thee beyond thy cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or lift vp thy thoughts aboue the pitch and meaſure of thy gifts, obſerue it with a iealous eie: further if it be an incentiue vnto euill, it is not <hi>a coale from the altar,</hi> but ſome wild fire caſt into thine heart, by <hi>Satan</hi> that old boutefeau. And if it ſpeake not <hi>according to the Law and the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie,</hi> there is deceit or vanity, falſhood or lightneſſe, but no light,<note place="margin">Eſay 8.20.</note> no weight of truth in it</p>
            <p>Againe from the former diſcourſe might ariſe another inference, as thus: That not euen the terrors and counter-commands of the greateſt, ſhould ſo interrupt vs in workes enioyned by God, as to make vs to deſiſt from them. For, <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to obey men ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than God, iudge yee, Acts</hi> 4.19.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16753:7"/>But the maine point, iſſuing from the refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of this text as of a parallel to that in <hi>Amos</hi> mentioned before, might be this: That like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions in this world oftentimes befall the good and the bad; yea that leſſer offenders are ſometimes chaſtened as more grieuous ſinners, and with the ſame rods: Gods people corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted as forreiners, true worſhippers as hated ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters; ſincere profeſſors as back-ſliding reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; <hi>Iuda</hi> here, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Amos</hi> there; and it may be euen now the true and cheerefull payer of his tithes to God, as the fraudulent and ſacrilegious man, and both with Blaſting and Mildew.</p>
            <p>This doctrine is a milke of Gods word to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh vs with comfort in all our troubles, &amp; ſucke it we may from the two breaſts of the Scriptures, the Old and New Teſtament: though wicked men by wreſting it wring out bloud, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thence as thoſe vngodly perſons in <hi>Malachi,</hi> and ſaying,<note place="margin">Malac. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>It is in vaine then to ſerue God, and what profit is it to keepe his commandements?</hi> But we haue I truſt better learned Chriſt, than to eſteeme gaine to be godlineſſe,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.6.</note> which of it ſelfe is the greateſt profit; and wee haue better learned his Croſſe, than to confound oyle with the lees, though both bee preſſed out with the ſame
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16753:7"/>
weight, and tumbled vp and downe in the ſame barrell; than not to put a difference (I meane) betweene the religious and the prophane, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both are vnder the ſame preſſure. Wheat is wheat, and chaffe is but chaffe, though both be beaten out with the ſame flaile. Stay we but a little Gods leiſure, till at his great comming hee purge his floore,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.18.</note> and wee ſhall diſcerne <hi>betweene the righteous and the wicked, betweene him that ſerueth God and him that ſerueth him not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 58. vlt.</note> For <hi>verily there is a reward for the righteous, doubtleſſe there is a God that iudgeth the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now hauing thus compared this Text with that in <hi>Amos,</hi> let vs conſider it in it ſelfe, as it offereth theſe two things to our meditation: Firſt, Gods mercy in correcting this people, <hi>I ſmote you with blaſting, and mildew, and haile, in all the workes of your hands.</hi> Then, their obſtinacie in not repenting, <hi>Yet yee haue not turned vnto mee, ſaith the Lord.</hi> I call this correction a worke of mercy; for beſides that all his chaſtenings are but haſtenings of his people to repentance, and that <hi>he ſcourgeth euery ſonne whom he receiueth;</hi> firſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.6.</note> here I ſee the rod in his owne hand; and it was <hi>Dauids</hi> choiſe ye know,<note place="margin">2 Sam 24.14.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs now fall into the hands of the Lord, (for his mercies are great) and let
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16753:8"/>
vs not fall into the hand of man.</hi> If I muſt be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, let my father himſelfe, and not his vaſſall chaſten me: his hand will not be too heauie on mee, whoſe heart cannot but be heauie for mee. <hi>In all my troubles the Lord himſelfe is troubled;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 63.9.</note> 
               <hi>Atque dolet quoties cogitur eſſe ferox.</hi> How ſhould it be otherwiſe?<note place="margin">Eccluſ. 2.18.</note> for <hi>as his maieſtie, ſuch is his mercie;</hi> both are infinite, and euerlaſting. This <hi>I</hi> in my Text then hath mercy in it; and the next word though it ſpeake of <hi>ſmiting,</hi> yet but of <hi>ſmiting.</hi> It is the Lords <hi>mercy,</hi> that when we are <hi>ſmitten</hi> of him,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.22.</note> 
               <hi>wee are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſsions faile not; I ſmote you. You:</hi> and it was but the earth which he ſmote, as parents ſtampe vpon the ground to fright their wayward children <hi>You:</hi> not their perſons, but the fruits and profits of their fields and vineyards. <hi>You:</hi> not the men by deſtroying them, but their corne, and wine, and oile, that by diminiſhing theſe things, they might haue recourſe vnto their heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſeeke their meat at God. So mothers deale with their little wantons, by taking the bread from them which they tread vnder foot: ſo nurſes with their babes, that firſt ſhew the breſt, and then put it vp againe, to make them ſearch the boſome, and cry for that food which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16753:8"/>
formerly they abuſed.<note place="margin">Eſa. 32.12.</note> He ſhewed them <hi>the breſts of the earth,</hi> that ſhould haue nouriſht them, fields ſtanding thicke with corne, oliues laden with their berries, and vines clogged with their grapes, and did but ſhew them, for <hi>he ſmote them with blaſting, and mildew, and haile.</hi> Nor was it want of mercy, by want to teach them the true worth and ſober vſe of theſe things. Nay he might haue ſmitten them with the ſword of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, whoſe mercies are crueltie; he might haue trodden their carcaſes as dung on the earth; or ſparing their liues, he might haue ſeized on their lands and vineyards, with fire from heauen, or flouds of water, (elements that haue no mercy) which might haue <hi>made a cleane riddance of all their food;</hi> but it was only <hi>with blaſting, and mildew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28.3.</note> 
               <hi>and haile,</hi> which are wont but to diminiſh, not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to periſh the good things of the land. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he might haue ſmitten them in the <hi>pleaſure of their eies,</hi> and the fruits of their loynes,<note place="margin">Ezek. 24.16.</note> I meane in their wiues and children; Yet it was but in the workes of their hands, in their fields which they had ſowne, in their Vineyards and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards which they had planted, and the like. So whether we conſider, Firſt the Author, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the Act, Thirdly the Obiect, Fourthly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16753:9"/>
the Inſtruments, or Fiftly, the manner of this correction, there is mercy in all. Mercy in the Author <hi>(I)</hi> a compaſſionate father. Mercy in the Act <hi>(I ſmote)</hi> not, I conſumed, Mercy in the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect <hi>(You)</hi> and not immediatly you, but yours, onely your corne, and wine, and oyle, &amp;c. Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the Inſtruments or rods <hi>(With Blaſting, and Mildew, and Haile,)</hi> not with ſword, or floud, or fire. Laſtly, Mercy in the manner <hi>(in the labours of your hands)</hi> not in the friends of their boſomes, or the fruits of their loynes, but onely in the fruits of their lands, and orchards, and gardens, which their hands had dreſſed and planted. So this part of my Text ſpeakes of compaſſion and correction, like <hi>Dauids</hi> Pſalme, that ſings of <hi>Mercy and Iudgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 101.1.</note> or of a mercifull chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; of rods ſteept not in brine, but in the oyle of loue. Yet (alas for their hardneſſe) all this oyle ſoftned not, nor could theſe rods beat them home to him that ſmote them, or bring them to a ſerious conſideration of the cauſe why they were thus afflicted: Yet <hi>yee returned not vnto me, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then wee haue a generall draught of my Text; wherein wee ſee all the parts and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaments of it. Now marke wee what mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16753:9"/>
of further obſeruation theſe in their order will afford.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the Author, <hi>I ſmote you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Author.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord. Blaſting, and Mildew, and Haile,</hi> were but mine inſtruments, I was the mouer, I ſtrooke you with theſe. The concluſion naturally iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hence is this:</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer bee the rods wherewith at any time we are chaſtened, for certaine the hand is Gods that correcteth vs. Be it dearth,<note place="margin">Leuit. 26.26.</note> it is he <hi>that breakes the ſtaffe of bread:</hi> or drought,<note place="margin">Deut. 11.17.</note> it is he <hi>that ſhuts the heauens:</hi> or deluge,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.11.</note> it is he <hi>that breakes vp all the fountaines of the deepe, and ſets open the cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racts or windowes of heauen.</hi> Be it fire, it is he <hi>that raines it:</hi> or ſtormie winde, it is he <hi>that ſends it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.24. Iona. 1.4. Pſalme 68.8.</note> Be it earthquake, it is <hi>his preſence that moues it:</hi> or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtrous aſpects of ſtarres and planets, it is hee <hi>that holds them all in his hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 38.31.</note> 
               <hi>that calls them by their names, that reſtraineth the ſweet influences of the Plei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ades, and looſeth the bands of Orion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.5.</note> Be it plague or peſtilence, they are <hi>his arrowes;</hi> or war,<note place="margin">Eſay 9.21.</note> it is <hi>his arme;</hi> or enemies, they are his <hi>armies;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 9.11.</note> for he is <hi>the Lord of Hoſts, and the ſhields of the world are his.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 47.9.</note> Briefly, there is no publique calamitie inflicted on man, or other creatures, of which wee may not ſay as the Prophet of the <hi>Aſsyrian</hi> tyrant,<note place="margin">Eſay 10.5.</note> that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16753:10"/>
it is <hi>the rod of Gods anger;</hi> though therewith hee ſtrike his children in loue: and a rod (ye know) cannot ſmite of it ſelfe, vnleſſe there be an hand to vſe it. Nor may all the hands in the world moue one of theſe rods, if God ſtretch not out his arme to ſtirre them. And as it is the Lord that ſends corrections in all common troubles, ſo is there no priuate affliction that betideth any without his prouidence, or without his hand, that ſmiteth by it. Therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged thus in his ſickneſſe;<note place="margin">Pſalme 32.4.</note> 
               <hi>Thine hand is heauy vpon me:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 38.3.</note> And againe, <hi>There is no health in my fleſh becauſe of thy diſpleaſure.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 38.2.</note> Therefore <hi>Ezekiah</hi> in his diſeaſe had recourſe to God <hi>by prayer:</hi> and holy <hi>Iob</hi> bereft of all worldly comforts, thus poſſeſt his ſoule by patience:<note place="margin">Iob 1.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord hath giuen, the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> Hee complaines not of the violence of the <hi>Shabeans,</hi> that droue away his oxen, nor of the iniuſtice of the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> that ſtole away his Camels, or of the cruelty of both, that ſlew his ſeruants: Nor doth he either execrate the fury of the fire, that burnt vp his ſheepe and ſhepherds; or curſe the boiſterouſneſſe of the winde, that blew downe the houſe, and there at once both killed and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried all his children: But thus he turned to him
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16753:10"/>
that ſmote him; <hi>The Lord hath giuen, the Lord hath taken away, &amp;c.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Ionas,</hi> though a very paſſionate man, (as appeareth by the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his propheſie) yet patiently tooke his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued affliction. And whereas the hands of the Mariners had heau'd him ouer ſhipboord, he ſaies it was the Lord that <hi>did caſt him into the bottome in the midſt of the ſea.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iona. 2.3.</note> Reuiling <hi>Shimei</hi> that threw ſtones at <hi>Dauid,</hi> with bitter obloquies (harder to be endured than ſtones themſelues) was yet himſelfe but as a ſtone throwne at <hi>Dauid</hi> by God, and therefore the holy man ſnarled not at that ſtone, but heeded the hand that caſt it;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.10.</note> 
               <hi>hee curſeth,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>becauſe the Lord hath bidden him curſe Dauid: Who then dare ſay, wherefore haſt thou done ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How then may not this iuſtly reproue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient ſpirits that ſpend themſelues in fretting at the meanes, or men by which the Lord doth chaſten them: like curſt Maſtiues that breake their teeth in gnawing thoſe iron chaines wherewith their maſters tie them, and in bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſtaffe wherewith he beats them. Doe but heare one complaine of his incurable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe contracted (it may be) or inflicted vpon him for his intemperancie; and yet though
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16753:11"/>
(according to the French prouerbe) <hi>he dig vp his owne graue with his teeth,</hi> he will both defame the noble Art of Phyſicke, and blame the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an which ſhould be <hi>honoured;</hi> not his owne bad diet, not his riot that cauſed the hand of God to ſmite him. Doe but obſerue another whom the heauy hand of oppreſſion (as he ſaith) hath brought low, and heare how hee breakes forth into diſmall curſings, and deepeſt execrations, fetched from the nethermoſt pit; as if hee would let looſe the Prince of darkneſſe, and all infernall powers againſt thoſe that wrong him: yet it may be, by idleneſſe and vnfaithfulneſſe in his calling, he hath ſuffered his eſtate to come to ruine, or hath let out his ſubſtance by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digalitie, or whoredome: notwithſtanding all his talke is againſt the iniquitie of men, or the hardneſſe of the times: not willing in the meane time either to remember his owne ſins or what the Scripture hath ſaid,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord maketh poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this time the Lord hath ſmitten vs in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts of the land with Blaſting and Mildew. The fulneſſe of our ſinnes, and the empty eares of corne, doe fearefully prognoſticate (ô let my feare proue falſe) a hungrie yeare.</p>
            <p>But if when <hi>one ſhall come to a mow or an heape of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16753:11"/>
twenty meaſures, he ſhall happen to finde but ten,</hi> let not the rich then complaine of Blaſting, or Mildew; nor let the poore cry out vpon cormorants, but let vs all remember what God ſaies heere in our Prophet, <hi>I ſmote you;</hi> the rich not vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedly, and the poore as worthily; the rich for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining at the former price, and the poore for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing the former plenty.</p>
            <p>To ſhut vp this point: Seeing it is our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father that ſtriketh, whatſoeuer be his ſcourge, with him let vs make our peace, to him our repeare. If to the creatures we crie for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, all may anſwer vs, as the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the diſtreſſed woman in a time of famine;<note place="margin">2 Kings 6.27.</note> 
               <hi>Seeing the Lord doth not ſuccour you, how ſhall wee helpe you with the barne or with the wine-preſſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 16.12.</note> If in our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes with <hi>Aſa</hi> we ſeeke firſt <hi>to the Phyſitian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 1.2.</note> or goe at all to <hi>the god of Ekron</hi> with <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> how iuſtly may the Lord make our maladies to be mortall, as were theirs? If in other diſtreſſes with <hi>Saul</hi> we haue recourſe to <hi>the Witch at Endor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28 11.</note> to Coniurers, or Wiſe men (falſly ſo called) we deſerue with him to be depriued both of life and grace, for ſeeking ſo to recouer loſſes. As therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> enquired of the woman of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.19.</note> if <hi>the hand of Ioab was not with her</hi> in that cloſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16753:12"/>
plea, and artificiall atonement which ſhe made for <hi>Abſolon;</hi> in all our troubles let vs enquire if there be not the hand of God in them; and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching we ſhall finde it is ſo: Which when wee haue found, let vs with patience reſigne vp our ſelues into his hands,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.18.</note> ſaying (as old <hi>Eli) It is the Lord, let him doe what ſeemeth him good.</hi> For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer be <hi>the rod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micah 6.9.</note> we haue heard now <hi>who appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it; I ſmote you, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> The Act.</note>
               <hi>I ſmote] Non niſi coactus percutit;</hi> Hee ſmites not till ſinners vrge him: and when he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, he doth but ſmite. Yet if he ſhould but ſmite vs according to his ſtrength, who could abide it, or endure his ſtrokes? He conſiders our weakneſſe, and the matter whereof we are made; elſe we being but as ſtubble, and he <hi>as a conſuming fire,</hi> how could we at all ſtand before him,<note place="margin">Pſalme 141.5.</note> and not finally periſh? Therefore he ſmites vs in mercy, and not in furie. As a tender hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Surgeon being to launce his childe, ſoftly handleth the ſore (ſaith <hi>Gregorie</hi>) before he ſtrikes, and then cutteth and weepeth, and weepeth and cutteth againe, <hi>Nec parcit vt parcat, nec miſeretur vt magis miſereatur,</hi> as <hi>S. Ierome</hi> ſpeaketh, (for otherwiſe ſparing would be ſpilling:) ſo deales this great Phyſitian of our ſoules; he ſmites but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16753:12"/>
to heale vs, and neuer ſtrikes vs but with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, mixing intreaties with his threatnings, <hi>O Ephraim what ſhall I doe vnto thee?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>O Iudah how ſhall I entreat thee?</hi> and euer mingling teares with his ſtrokes which he muſt giue vs,<note place="margin">Luke 19.41.</note> as hee <hi>wept ouer Ieruſalem,</hi> which <hi>Titus</hi> that ſcourge of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> was afterwards to whip and weepe for. The latter <hi>Rabbines</hi> tell vs a ſtory, or a fiction ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (and you will not beleeue it if I tell you, nor will I tell it to that end) that God hath a ſecret retiring place, to which at certaine times, he vſeth to withdraw himſelfe euery day, where bewailing the deſolation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſperſion of the <hi>Iewes</hi> with many teares, he doth beſhrew himſelfe that in his anger hee ſubuerted the Temple and holy citie. This do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of theirs (if you take it in the literall ſenſe as they ſeeme to doe) is little better than a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. But vnderſtand it ſpiritually, and the meaning may be that of the Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>I am ſore vexed for the hurt of the daughter of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> or that of <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 54.8.</note> 
               <hi>For a moment in mine anger I hid my face from thee:</hi> or that in the Prophet <hi>Ionas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iona. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord repented him of the euill that he had ſaid.</hi> Which muſt not be ſo vnderſtood as if God were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to repentance or to paſſions; but becauſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16753:13"/>
hee, who is immutability in the higheſt degree, doth ſpeake with thoſe that are mutable after the manner of them with whom hee ſpeaketh, ſaith <hi>Gregorie.</hi> And therefore lift vp that groſſe relation of the <hi>Rabbines</hi> from an earthly to an heauenly acception; and it is true, that God takes ſo little pleaſure in puniſhing of his people, that (were it poſſible for the thrice ſacred and all place filling Deity, to immure it ſelfe into a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholicke cell, and there to bee diſſolued into teares) he would euer weepe and grieue for them. As then <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh of a good man,<note place="margin">Pſalme 141.5.</note> let vs ſay of God, <hi>O let the righteous,</hi> my righteous and mercifull father, <hi>ſmite me, for that is a benefit:</hi> If we muſt be chaſtened, happy are we that we ſmart by his ſmitings: <hi>Let him reproue vs and it ſhall be a precious oyle:</hi> For this wee may bee ſure of, that when his correction comes, <hi>Nec venit ſine meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to quia Deus eſt juſtus, nec erit ſine commodo quia Deus eſt bonus;</hi> It neither comes without our merit that haue deſerued it, for God is iuſt, nor ſhall it be but to our profit, becauſe he is good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
            <p>Further in this act of their correction hee ſpeakes, you ſee, of that which was paſt and done; <hi>I ſmote</hi>] which againe implieth another
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16753:13"/>
note of Gods mercy: for in that he ſaith, <hi>I ſmote,</hi> he ſaies in effect, and by conſequent, that for the preſent he had laid aſide his rod, and now had ceaſed from ſmiting, though as yet they had neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to build againe the Temple, for which neglect hee had thus corrected them. Surely ſhould not he giue ouer puniſhing, till we giue ouer altogether ſinning, he ſhould neuer make an end till there were an end of vs; for we are but as lead to the fire of trouble: ſhould he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe from refining of vs in that fire, till all our droſſe were purged, he might conſume our very ſubſtance, and leaue vs nothing.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.14.</note> Yet <hi>he hath deuiſed a meanes not to caſt out his baniſhed:</hi> and hath promiſed <hi>to purifie and refine vs as gold and ſiluer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Malach. 3.3. Eſay 1.25.</note> 
               <hi>to burne out all our droſſe, and to take away all our tinne,</hi> but it muſt be then (as the Prophets meant it) by another fire than affliction, euen the power of Gods word, from the vertue of his ſpirit, of which the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> thus;<note place="margin">Matth. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall baptized you with the Holy Ghoſt and with fire.</hi> Therefore the Lord to magnifie his powerfull mercy hauing ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this people (<hi>I ſmote you,</hi> ſaith hee) comes to trie as it were another courſe with them: and ſends them a Prophet who by three weekes prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and a little more,<note place="margin">Hag. 1.1.</note> (for <hi>the word came to Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16753:14"/>
the firſt day of the ſixth moneth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. 2. cap. 1.</note> and <hi>the twenty fourth day of the ſame moneth they began to build</hi>) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained that of them which forty yeeres correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could not extort.<note place="margin">Hag. 1.15.</note> So powerfull is the word of God: ſo true that which he ſaith by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,<note place="margin">Eſay 55.11.</note> 
               <hi>The word which goeth out of my mouth ſhall not returne vnto me void, it ſhall accompliſh that which I will, and proſper in the thing to which I ſend it.</hi> And thus as <hi>the Lord will not be euer chiding,</hi> ſo not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies correcting; and oftentimes hee doth that by the word of his mouth, which many ſtripes could not effect: For hee is not as <hi>Moſes,</hi> which could doe no great worke without the rod in his hand; but laying aſide his ſcourges he doth eftſoones by the powerfull operation of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit, worke the conuerſion of his people: for ſo he ſpeakes in <hi>Hoſea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Behold I will allure them and ſpeake friendly vnto them;</hi> hee had ſaid before that he would <hi>take away from them his corne in the time thereof, and his wine in the ſeaſon thereof, that he would recouer from them the wooll,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 9.</note> 
               <hi>and the flax, which he had lent to couer their ſhame;</hi> that he would <hi>deſtroy their vines and figtrees;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 12.</note> that he would <hi>make them as a forreſt, and that the wilde beasts ſhould eat them, &amp;c.</hi> But then remembring his mercy, he makes this promiſe; <hi>Behold I will allure, behold I will ſpeake friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16753:14"/>
O the neuer too much admired goodneſſe of the Lord, that leaues no meanes vnattempted to procure our good! As here when ſmiting could not preuaile, hee ſends a Prophet to perſwade; who yet muſt tell them that the Lord had ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them. That they may remember their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction wherewith the Lord hath chaſtened them and their fathers for the ſpace now of forty yeeres, they muſt heare of it, though it bee paſt and done.</p>
            <p>And this in the next place importeth our dutie, as before it implied a note of Gods mercy. Conceiue it thus: When troubles haue done with vs, we muſt not ſo haue done with them: former afflictions, though paſt and gone, would yet not be forgotten: therefore the Lord here puts them in minde what he hath done, what they and their fathers haue ſuffered; <hi>I ſmote you.</hi> And this very thing he wiſheth them in this chapter, once and againe, and the third time, to <hi>conſider of.</hi> Wee like it well that our children ſhould not forget when and for what wee haue corrected them: but him that remembers the rod no longer than he ſmarts by it, wee hold a careleſſe ſonne. It is an argument of a diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion almoſt incorrigible, ſo to deſpiſe Gods ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16753:15"/>
as to be no longer mindfull than wee are ſenſible of them, or no longer to ſorrow for ſinne than we ſuffer for it. Yet all of vs are too too like <hi>Ioab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.31.</note> that would not goe to <hi>Abſolon</hi> till he had ſet his corne on fire: and I wiſh a many of vs were not worſe; for the Lord hath ſent a blaſting or (as the word here ſignifies) a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning winde into our fields, and yet how few (as it may be iuſtly feared) haue recourſe to God that ſmites them? Though that neither be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, I meane only to <hi>viſit him in our troubles,</hi> then and neuer elſe to <hi>poure out a praier but when his chaſtening is vpon vs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 26.16.</note> We hold him ſcarce a friend that neuer comes to ſee vs but when ſome exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencie driues him; and it is but forced homage which we doe to our heauenly King, when by praier and repentance we repeare not to him, vnleſſe he ſend a Purſeuant of affliction for vs. Our greateſt motiues to turne vnto him ſhould be his mercies; but if wee will not ſtirre but when the ſpurre is in our ſides, there is but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle good metall in vs. If we be generous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſuch as <hi>ſo runne that we may obtaine,</hi> not miſeries only preſent, but their very memorie will haſten vs. As then it is <hi>good for vs to haue beene in trouble,</hi> ſo euer to remember it. And here
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16753:15"/>
in few words let me heape vp many reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is an excellent meanes to keepe the heart lowly, ſtill to haue in minde what wee or ours haue beene, or haue ſuffered. He that of a Potters ſon became afterwards a <hi>Sicilian</hi> Prince, is renowned for it, that he would be ſerued at his Table partly in earthen veſſels, to remember him daily of his former meane condition or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage; and partly in veſſels of gold and ſiluer, that he might not forget himſelfe to be a King. Surely as our aduancement to the ſtate of grace ſhould put vs in minde to walke worthy of our calling, ſo the remembrance of our creation and mould of our corruption alſo and former croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for them ſhould quell our ſwelling, and keepe vs lowly. When the Prophet would take downe the pride and boaſting of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> he puts them in remembrance of the afflictions of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from whom they were deſcended:<note place="margin">Hoſea 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>Iaakob</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>fled into the countrey of Aram, and Iſrael ſerued for a wife, and for a wife he kept ſheepe.</hi> As if he had ſaid; If you boaſt of your riches and nobilitie, you ſeeme to reproach your father, who was a poore, but an honeſt fugitiue, and a ſeruant. And thus the greateſt houſes, would they but reſpect the rock from which they were
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16753:16"/>
digged out, may finde beggerie or pouertie in their firſt foundations; for there is no nobilitie whoſe baſe on which it ſtood, was not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times baſeneſſe, and which God cannot againe reſolue into its former principles of meanneſſe and obſcuritie.</p>
            <p>Againe, the memorie of former troubles keepes the minde watchfull, and makes a man more warie, for <hi>what hath beene may be againe,</hi> and <hi>there is nothing new vnder the Sunne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.9.</note> He that hath once ſurfetted by feeding on ſome diſh, doth vſually for euer after loath it: but if he will to it againe, in his ſickneſſe let him blame himſelfe. <hi>Improbè Neptunum accuſat, qui iterum naufragium fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit;</hi> He that will needs to the ſea, hauing once made ſhipwracke, if he fall foule the ſecond time, may thanke himſelfe. If then by thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer enormities thou haſt ſometimes gotten a weakneſſe to thy body, or a wound to thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, a blot to thy name, or a diſparagement to thy calling; if for thine iniquities thou haſt beene corrected in thy goods or friends, in thine oliue or her branches, thy wife or children, or howſoeuer elſe, forget not theſe former croſſes, the remembrances whereof may be ſoueraigne preſeruatiues againſt future ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:16753:16"/>Thirdly, as conqueſts in former battels adde hope and confirmation to valour in ſucceeding wars, ſo the memorie of former difficulties which by grace we haue once ouercome, giues ſtrength to faith, and hope to patience, and comfort by them both, when wee ſhall bee brought to combat with new aſſaults. So the Lion and the Beare which <hi>Dauid</hi> could remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber he had ſlaine,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.35, 36.</note> encouraged him to grapple with the Giant.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, to be much and frequent in this meditation, ſets a greater price vpon Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings while we haue them, the worth whereof wee better vnderſtand by calling to minde our former wants of them. And therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> more ſeriouſly to affect the people with a true ſenſe of their libertie and deliuerance, ſo often puts them in minde of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, it teacheth compaſſion towards others in the like afflictions. If there bee ought (I ſay not of grace, but) of good nature in vs, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but commiſerate others in their troubles, when we call to memorie our owne. Thus to moue the Iſraelites to tender heartedneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſtrangers and ſeruants, that man of God tels them againe,<note place="margin">Deut. 16.12.</note> 
               <hi>that they were ſeruants in the land of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16753:17"/>
Egypt.</hi> And ſhould not this argument preuaile with Chriſtian maſters as much, if not more than with <hi>Iewes;</hi> ſeeing <hi>Chriſt</hi> of <hi>Satans</hi> vaſſals hath made them free deniſons aboue?</p>
            <p>Briefly it ſtirres vp the heart to continuall thankfulneſſe, when together with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our former troubles, wee cannot but be mindfull of Gods mercies that either ceaſed or eaſed, or ſo ſeaſoned thoſe troubles, that with patience we bore them, and that the nets being broken, our ſoules at length eſcaped and were ſet free. The Church ſtories report, that the woman cured by our Sauiour of her iſſue of bloud,<note place="margin">Luke 8.44.</note> 
               <hi>onely by touching the hemme of his garment,</hi> returning to her houſe at Philippi, cauſed two Statues to bee ſet before her doores, one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling her ſelfe an humble ſuppliant on her knees with her hands lifted vp; another reſembling our Sauiour, ſtretching forth his hands vnto her: at the feet of which picture (couered as it were with a robe) there did grow vp ſo high as the hemme of it, an herbe called <hi>Panace,</hi> which that age (as <hi>Plinie</hi> alſo more than two hundred yeeres before <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi>) ſeemed to haue held ſoueraigne againſt all diſeaſes. Theſe trophees which ſhee had
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16753:17"/>
ſet vp in the honour of Chriſt, were to be ſeene (ſaith the ſame <hi>Euſebius</hi>) in his time, that is, at leaſt three hundred yeeres after Chriſt. Well, to what purpoſe ſerues this hiſtorie? Thus: All are not able with this woman to erect before our houſes in the honour of our great Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, ſuch monuments as may remember vs of his mercy ſo often as wee goe in or out by our doores: but all may and ſhould daily ſet vp before the eyes of their minde a two-fold <hi>Memento;</hi> one of their former calamities which they haue felt, by ſuffering; another of Gods fauours which they haue proued by his deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Which would we doe, hence would grow a wonderfull meaſure of thankfulneſſe, a grace moſt acceptable to God for former bleſſings, and of a catholike medicinall vertue againſt all times of future euils: for not Crucifixes worne in our boſomes or about vs, but former croſſes together with Gods ancient mercies borne in faithfull memorie, are powerfull amulets to ſaue vs from the euill of enſuing dangers. If then the Lord hath ſmitten vs, know it is our dutie with <hi>Ephraim to ſmite our ſelues vpon the thigh,</hi> and to remember the corrections of old.<note place="margin">Ier. 31.19.</note> Could the Iron be pliable and faſhionable to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16753:18"/>
minde of the Smith after a few ſtrokes, nor could he but willingly ſpare his armes, nor ſhould it need more often heating or beating afterwards. Would our ſtifneſſe relent with the firſt croſſe, and be conformable to God that frames vs to his will, we ſhould ſaue God a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and our ſelues a ſecond trouble. <hi>I ſmote you</hi> (ſaith he) remember it, that I may ſmite you no more.</p>
            <p>And thus farre touching the Author and the Act of this correction: now ſee the Obiect; <hi>You.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſmote you]</hi> not their perſons (as I ſaid before) but their fields and vineyards, or in theſe, their corne and grapes, and the like. Yet in that hee bleſt not theſe, it was as if he had blaſted them. For though ſuch things be not our life, yet they are our liuelihood; though not the flame, yet the oyle that feeds it. And therefore to affect them more feelingly with theſe afflictions, hee tels them, that whiles but theſe things were ſtrucken, themſelues were ſmitten; <hi>I ſmote you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take out this leſſon then: We ſhould be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the calamities that befall the creatures, for we are croſſed if they be curſed for our ſakes.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16753:18"/>
If the Lord at this time, partly by Blaſting and Mildew, partly by vnſeaſonable weather, haue weakened our ſtaffe of bread; weakned, I ſay; (for bleſſed be his mercy that he hath not yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together broken it) Iudge we our ſelues,<note place="margin">Hab. 3.8.</note> to bee deſeruedly ſmitten: For, <hi>Behold we haue ſinned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.</note> 
               <hi>we haue done wickedly,</hi> but the corne and other fruits of the earth, <hi>what haue they done?</hi> Nay, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane gluttonie of the times, that men feede themſelues without feare; The loathſome drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe of the times, that men drinke by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and yet without meaſure; The wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the times, that men <hi>like fed horſes neigh after</hi> vnlawfull luſts, are ſinnes that haue made the whole body of our nation foule and very filthy. No maruell then if to purge ſuch foule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſuch filthineſſe, God doe euen now threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vs with a famine and cleaneneſſe of teeth. The father of Phyſitians tells vs, that a foule bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the more it is nouriſhed, the more it is peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: and that a plethorique body would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a preſent euacuation. And is it not in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall matters as in corporall things? We are all Gods patients, and he our great Phyſitian. Now the body of our ſins (which the Apoſtle calleth <hi>a body of death</hi>) is growne ſo full, ſo foule,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16753:19"/>
without purging there can bee no hope of the life of grace. It therefore it ſhall pleaſe him ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take away his corne or the vertue of it, and to <hi>ſend leaneneſſe into our ſoules</hi> (as <hi>Dauid</hi> phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the worſt of famines,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 106.15.</note> 
               <hi>when men eat and are not ſatisfied</hi>) he doth it in wiſdome to procure cleaneneſſe of ſoule. For certaine if our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne ſinnes did not require a ſlender diet, we ſhould not need to feare a dearth,<note place="margin">Reu. 6.</note> that <hi>Blacke horſe,</hi> as the Scripture calls it, after which two vſually followeth <hi>the pale horſe whoſe rider is death.</hi> But now that I am about for this time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude my labour, and that I would not that it ſhould ſet in ſo blacke a cloud as is a threatning, heare I pray you the wholeſome words of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; <hi>Let vs ceaſe to doe euill, and learne to doe well, and he will nouriſh vs,</hi> for hee hath promiſed to feed ſuch, euen <hi>in the time of dearth.</hi> Surely, if we will <hi>heare and obey,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 1.</note> 
               <hi>we ſhall eat the good things of the land;</hi> our ſtore ſhall be plenteous, and our porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fat:<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>he will render vnto vs the yeares which the Graſhopper hath eaten:</hi> I meane, he will turne Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting into a bleſſing, Mildew and Haile, into a gracious raine vpon his inheritance, and the <hi>fields ſhall ſtand ſo thicke with corne, that they ſhall laugh and ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:16753:19"/>But in the meane time, let vs more deſire that precious food of our ſoules, the word of God which endureth for euer, than the things of this life which muſt certainly periſh. And thus far touching, firſt, the Author: ſecondly, the Act; thirdly the Obiect of this correction; in theſe words, <hi>I ſmote you.</hi> The rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant you muſt expect at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time. <hi>Till then and euer the Lord giue a bleſsing to that which hath beene ſaid.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16753:20"/>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:16753:20"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HAGGAI 2.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I ſmote you with Blaſting, and with Mildew, and with Haile, in all the labours of your hands: Yet ye turned not to me, ſaith the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Text heere parted it ſelfe into two ſtreames, like that riuer <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera</hi> in <hi>Sicilie</hi> (as it is reported) the one ſomewhat ſalt, rather well ſeaſoned, which I called Gods mercifull corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this people, <hi>I ſmote you with Blaſting, and Mildew, and Haile, in all the labours of your hands:</hi> the other freſh and vnſauory, hauing no ſalt teares of true repentance in it; <hi>Yet yee turned not vnto me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> In the former I noted, firſt,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16753:21"/>
the Author, <hi>(I)</hi> ſecondly, the Act, <hi>(ſmote)</hi> thirdly, the Obiect, <hi>(You)</hi> (points already hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with their ſeuerall obſeruations) fourthly, the rods or inſtruments with which hee ſmote them, <hi>Blaſting, Mildew, Haile;</hi> fiftly, the manner of this correction, or the things wherein hee ſmote them, <hi>In all the labours of your hands:</hi> which two laſt particulars (the remanents of the firſt part) muſt now be ſet before you, and after that I ſhall preſent you with the ſecond generall, and all at this time, as God ſhall giue abilitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> The rods.</note>
               <hi>With Blaſting, and with Mildew, and with Haile]</hi> Theſe are the rods wherewith the Lord ſmote them, which though they ſeeme to be bound vp in one bundle, and to make but one clauſe in my text, are yet ſeuerall corrections and diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in themſelues. The laſt of them, which is <hi>Haile,</hi> none but knowes both that it is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thing from the other two, and how it hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the fruits of the earth, ſometimes in the bud, ſometimes in the bloſſome, ſometimes inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting their growth, ſometimes daſhing both them and our hopes when they are come to their ripenes &amp; maturity. But for the two former, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is their difference ſo plaine, nor their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in annoying the profits of the ground ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16753:21"/>
apparant to ſenſe, till they haue done the hurt. And yet if we marke it well, the Scripture doth diſtinguiſh them both heere and whereſoeuer elſe they are mentioned, though generally it bring them in thus yoaked together,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.22. 1 Kings 8.37.</note> 
               <hi>Blaſting and Mildew;</hi> for firſt if the originall here bee conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the words run thus, <hi>With Blaſting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 4.9. Hag. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>and with Mildew, and with Haile;</hi> not thus, with Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting or Mildew. Secondly, the Scripture ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpeakes of theſe two, but it doth expreſſe them by words that cannot bee confounded, tearmes I meane ſo different in ſignification that they cannot be wrought to note the ſame thing; for that which we call <hi>Blaſting,</hi> the Hebrew na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Shidaphon;</hi> which ſome tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, a corruption of, or by the winde; the Septuagint <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a combuſtion or aduſtion: others <hi>vredinem;</hi> others <hi>ventum vrentem,</hi> a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning winde; others <hi>ventum orientalem,</hi> a ſcorching Eaſt winde. And that which we call <hi>Mildew,</hi> the Hebrew termeth <hi>Ierakon,</hi> which comes of the root <hi>Iarak</hi> that ſignifies to ſpit, as if Mildew were <hi>Saliua ſiderum,</hi> ſaith one, an excrementitious humor, which the ſtarres ſpit downe vpon the fruits of the earth, and which makes them to become abortiue, as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſpeaketh. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16753:22"/>
though he ſeeme to confound theſe two <hi>Blaſting &amp; Mildew,</hi> yet the Maker of Nature, God himſelfe, who knew more than <hi>Plinie</hi> a ſearcher of it, hath in his neuer-deceiuing word (as it ſeemes to mee) put a plaine difference betweene theſe two. Which <hi>Vatablus</hi> obſeruing, ſets this note vpon my text, <hi>Haec ſunt duo vitia ſegetum, quorum vnum nimia ſiccitate &amp; aeſtu prouenit, alterum nimia humiditate:</hi> Theſe are two calamities in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to corne, whereof the one proceedeth of too much drought, the other of too much moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. And here I doe not finde any Expoſitor to ſpeake ſo fully of this point, as my text ſeemes to require, and I could wiſh; and therefore might I but a little with your patience ſpeake as a Philoſopher in differencing theſe two (I meane as a Philoſopher no waies repugning the ſacred truth of Diuinitie) I ſhould thinke <hi>Blaſting,</hi> to be referred to an hurtfull winde; and <hi>Mildew,</hi> to an vnkindly moiſture. And firſt for Blaſting, the very word implies a winde: and winde of it ſelfe is by nature hot and dry, as is the exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is the matter of it. But as the ſonne of <hi>Syrach</hi> ſpeakes of ſpirits,<note place="margin">Eccluſ. 39.28.</note> may I ſay, <hi>There bee windes which are created for vengeance:</hi> ſo there are hurtfull windes, as there are hurtfull ſpirits,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16753:22"/>
and blaſting I take to be the effect of ſuch. This once, Philoſophie and our owne experience teacheth, that winde is of a piercing nature by reaſon of the ſubtleneſſe of it, which openeth and entereth the pores or ſecret paſſages, in all bodies penetrable. So that whether it be ioyned with froſt, it lets in the cold into tender bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes of trees, and into other fruits of the earth in their Milke or infancie, and ſo kils them in the Wombe, as it were, and cauſeth the earth or trees to miſcarry their fruits by vntimely blighting: or whether it be accompanied with ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie heat of the Sunne, eſpecially in the morning, after cold and froſtie nights; it par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth and drieth more vehemently. For as winde and heat by nature, ſo froſt is alſo a drier by a certaine <hi>antiperiſtaſis,</hi> (as they call it) when one qualitie encompaſſed with another that is contrary, is intended or made more vehement; like greateſt ſpirits that neuer expreſſe more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, than when they are moſt narrowed and encloſed in the greateſt ſtraits. Now as all windes are of themſelues hot and drie, ſo the Eaſtwinde eſpecially, and therefore in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we finde, that <hi>to dry vp fountaines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 13.15.</note> and <hi>to dry vp the fruits of the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 19.12.</note> is aſcribed to the <hi>Eaſterne
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16753:23"/>
winde.</hi> Yea let the dreame of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> confirme what I ſay:<note place="margin">Gen. 41.6.</note> for the <hi>ſeuen thinne eares of corne</hi> there mentioned, are ſaid to be <hi>burned</hi> or <hi>blaſted,</hi> and that <hi>with an Eaſtlie winde.</hi> So then it is the winde that doth blaſt, eſpecially the Eaſt winde in thoſe places; yet not euery Eaſt winde, but onely ſuch as by a faintie or ſultrie blowing openeth the pores, and prouoketh ſweat; as that which cauſed <hi>Ionas</hi> to faint,<note place="margin">Iona. 4.8.</note> and which <hi>Iunius</hi> and <hi>Tremellius</hi> doe tranſlate <hi>Eurum ſilentem, a calme Eaſt winde,</hi> to diſtinguiſh it from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ruffling Eaſt winde that <hi>breakes the ſhips of Tharſhiſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 48.7.</note> This I take to be blaſting. That there is a blighting ſometimes in thunder by light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning I grant: but that which the Scripture ſpeakes of here, and in other places, is vſually by a feruent (not a boiſterous) but a burning Eaſt winde, as ſundry Tranſlators giue it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, thoſe hot exhalations which cauſe thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and lightning, are alſo the matter of the winde, as naturall Philoſophie teacheth. Now for <hi>Mildew,</hi> whether it be ſo called becauſe it is a <hi>mild-dew,</hi> or a <hi>milb-tewe</hi> (as ſome thinke) of the German word <hi>milben,</hi> that ſignifies a worme or moth that conſumeth garments, becauſe it is as a moth or conſumption to ſome fruits of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16753:23"/>
earth, and in ſome breedeth a kinde of worme that eats them; or whether it be ſo termed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a <hi>mal-dew,</hi> that is, an hurtfull dew, or becauſe it is a <hi>mel-dew,</hi> that is, a honey dew which doth this harme, is not much materiall to know, nor can I determine. But either wee may conceiue it to be a rotten dew, (as Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers call it) which by a hurtfull touch ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the growth of ſome fruits of the earth that are obnoxious to it, as on the contrary whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome dew doth nouriſh them: or ſome putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying miſt which makes them to ruſt, eating out their ſtate and ſubſtance, as canker fretteth iron; and this the Latine word <hi>rubigo</hi> (which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>mildew</hi> as well as <hi>ruſt</hi>) ſeemes to import: For as there are winds that doe blaſt, as well as winds that blow vitally and refreſhingly, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the earth to fructifie, which are therefore called <hi>Zephyrus</hi> and <hi>Venti Fauonij,</hi> becauſe they quicken and foſter the increaſe of the earth; ſo we may conceiue that there are ſome dewes and miſts which doe hurt, as well as others that doe helpe the growth of fruits. Or laſtly, might I here interpoſe what I thinke, I ſhould ſay that ſhrinking of corne by <hi>Mildew</hi> might be thus: Namely, That in fields leſſe peruious and open
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16753:24"/>
to cleere &amp; ſtrong winds, (as in lower grounds, or other places betweene woods and hils) there fall oftentimes ſultrie and foggie miſts; and theſe couering and keeping too cloſe the fruits of the ground vnder them, as vnder thicke man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, doe caſt that corne or kind of graine which is ſubiect to this maladie, as it were, into an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly ſweat, at ſuch time as the eares thereof are not yet ſufficiently filled from the root. By which faint ſweat is vented that ſweetneſſe which ſhould feed the eare. Now this ſweetneſſe once exhauſted or drawne out at the ſtalke or ſtraw, ſticks cloſe vnto it being burnt or made aduſt, by ſome extraordinary heat of the Sunne, as it happeneth, eſpecially in the Canicula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dayes, which (as it may ſeeme) made the <hi>Romans</hi> to ſacrifice a dogge to <hi>Mildew,</hi> as <hi>Ouid</hi> tels vs. So that in corne thus ſmitten we may behold the ſtraw ſpeckled with blacke ſpots as it were of ſoot, which I take to be nothing elſe but the ſweet moiſture of the reede exhaled in a faint ſweat through a foggie miſt or <hi>Mildew,</hi> and then afterwards by ſome extraordinary heat turned into a burnt and blacke matter. But be it what it is: he that ſends it, knowes it; And therefore leauing this ſpeculation, ſeeing the Lord hath
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16753:24"/>
but of late ſmitten vs in our grounds with <hi>a burning wind, and with Mildew,</hi> know it is our duty not ſo much to diſpute or enquire what they are, and whence they come, as to ſeeke how by teares of repentance to quench that fire of his anger that ſent this burning into our fields. So by maturely conuerting now vnto him, wee ſhall preuent the next yeeres like affliction, haue this ſanctified vnto vs, and bee freed for euer from the terrors of that neuer dying fire.</p>
            <p>Yet I haue not done with this clauſe, till hence I haue gathered ſome obſeruations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With Blaſting, and Mildew, and Haile]</hi> With theſe he ſmote them. Theſe then are but rods, they are not gods or goddeſſes, as the heathen thought them. The <hi>Thurij</hi> in <hi>Aelian</hi> made a Deitie of the winde, and the Romanes ſet vp Mildew for a goddeſſe, as Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> tels vs. And both (ô ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculouſly abſurd idolatry!) offered ſacrifice to them. But I will not be ſo vnthrifty as to ſpend one word in refelling ſo groſſe a ſuperſtition. A bare narration, is confutation enough for ſo childiſh a folly. Nor had I vouchſafed ſo much as once to mention it, but to reproue ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that laugh at theſe Idols, and yet ſet vp others in their ſtead. Outward proſperity who
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16753:25"/>
deſires not? yet to dote vpon it ſo much, as to haue our affections clung to it, and <hi>ſet</hi> altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>vpon the things below,</hi> what is it but to adore an idoll? And yet how many bee there that euen proſtitute their ſoules before it, and ſticke not to ſacrifice both a good name and a good conſcience to demerit it? And what is worldly proſperity (to ſpeake in a worldlings language) but Fortunes ſultry winde? indeed a ſpirituall blaſting that ſhrinkes and blighteth vertue in her growth? For as the riuer <hi>Nilus,</hi> when it ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth too high, and waters <hi>Aegypt</hi> ouer-much, makes the land barren, which otherwiſe by a meane flowing would cauſe it to fructifie: ſo the world when it comes too faſt vpon vs with an ouer-ſwelling redundancie, choakes the ſeed of Gods graces in vs, and makes the ſoule fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, as that riuer doth the ſoile. It is an <hi>aphoriſme</hi> in Phyſicke, that fulneſſe in the extreme is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie vnto health: And tis an axiome in Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that exceſſiue plentie is no friend to grace. For as <hi>miſfortunes ſlay the wicked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.20.</note> ſo <hi>the proſperity of fooles deſtroyeth them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 1.32.</note> Therefore <hi>Agur</hi> praied thus, <hi>Giue me not pouerty nor riches, but feed mee with food conuenient for me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 30.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>leſt I be full and deny thee, or leſt I be poore and ſteale.</hi> Yea of the two, aduerſity
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16753:25"/>
it ſelfe is leſſe aduerſe to goodneſſe than carnall eaſe and abundance: as it is not the boyſtrous winde that hurteth the fruit of the earth, ſo much as a faint and ſultry blowing. It was not the ruffling winde, but the ſcorching beames of the Sunne, that made the man lay aſide his cloke, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> hath it in a parable.</p>
            <p>Worldly proſperity cauſeth many to put off the garment of holineſſe and innocencie, which they buckled faſt vnto them, whiles they were exerciſed with ſtormes of troubles. The zeale of Chriſtians is like that <hi>ignis Graecus,</hi> which (as a Philoſopher ſpeaketh) is enflamed by powring cold water vpon it; or like our Engliſh Ieat, that is fired in water and quenched with oyle, (as a learned country man of our owne obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth) for it hath euer growne more feruent by affliction, and proſpered leſſe in times of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Thus the Halcyon daies of the Church ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing but breathed a little betweene the ninth &amp; tenth perſecution, brought forth contentions amongſt the learned, and much hypocriſie in all ſorts, which prouoked Gods iudgements, as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> noteth. It is the warmth of Goats bloud (ſaith <hi>Solinus</hi>) that diſſolues the Adamant, when neither hammer nor other maſſie engines of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16753:26"/>
can breake it. And it is the heat of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, which weakens vertue more than many heauy troubles. Therefore to be too far in loue with worldly felicity, that ſo blighteth good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and pietie, what is it but with the <hi>Thurij</hi> to make an idoll of the winde, and to be in loue with blaſting? Againe, giue another inſtance; ſome are ſo far in loue with their ſinnes, as that they hate a reprouer, and doe loue nothing more than flatttery that ſtroketh them: and what is this but with the <hi>Romans</hi> to ſacrifice to Mildew? for hony tongues of paraſites, doe more hurt than hony-dewes: theſe marre but that which ſhould be our meat, but thoſe corrupt the man himſelfe, who (it may be) would diſrelliſh his faults, and abhor them, did not pleaſing adula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wrap them vp in ſugred ſpeeches, and cauſe him to ſwallow them downe without ſenſe or conſcience. For other mens ſinnes are direct ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to our eies, but our owne ſinnes, like our owne eies, we ſee not but by reflexion either of conſcience within, or of others information without vs. Which if they bee falſe and flatter vs, how eaſily doe we yeeld our ſelues to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with ſuch ſophiſtrie. The chiefe reaſon whereof is the ſelfe-loue of our owne deceitfull
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16753:26"/>
hearts, which expoſeth vs ouer-credulous to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deceitfull tongues, &amp; willingly lookes not on ought that is euill in vs: As the mother of the <hi>Minotaure</hi> in her naturall affection to that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter could neuer endure to looke vpon the beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part of it; ſome loue their ſinnes as their owne ſonnes, vnwilling to reflect their eies vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that monſtrous fouleneſſe that is in them, therefore they hate the very glaſſe of true dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that would repreſent vnto them ſuch fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe: Whereas the deceitfull ſpectacles of falſe flatterie, which ſhewes their good parts (if they haue any) greater and better than they are indeed, they put in their boſomes, and hold ſuch for deareſt and moſt intimate friends, as haue learned the flattering ſtile. Yet the Greeke Oratour <hi>Demosthenes</hi> thought it better to fall amongſt rauens than paraſites, for thoſe feede vpon the dead, theſe eat vp the liuing. But I haue held you too long in a figure: for worldly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity is a Blaſting, and flattery is a Mildew, but both in the Metaphor. Come wee now to the letter, and there obſerue how theſe three rods come in bound vp together with a coniunctiue, With; <hi>With Blaſting,</hi> ſaith the Prophets, <hi>With Mildew, and with Haile.</hi> For the two former I finde
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16753:27"/>
in Scripture that if one be ſpoken of,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.22. 1 King. 8.37. Amos 4.9. Hag. 2.17.</note> the other is mentioned alſo, and ſaue one place that is the 41. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> I finde not any place wherein they are not brought in, coupled thus, <hi>with Blaſting and Mildew.</hi> Nor is it a wonder that Gods corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſhould come by couples at leaſt, or by leaſhes as heere, <hi>Blaſting, Mildew, Haile,</hi> when mens corruptions goe not only by cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.13.</note> 
               <hi>Gluttonie and drunkenneſſe, chambering and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, ſtrife and enuying;</hi> but thus in troupes; <hi>There is no truth, nor mercy, nor knowledge of God in the Land. By ſwearing, and lying, and killing, and ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſe. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>and whoring, men breake out, and bloud toucheth bloud.</hi> For ſhould not full viols of wrath be pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red downe on <hi>men full of all vnrighteouſneſſe,</hi> and thoſe other ſinnes named by the Apoſtle, which are ſo monſtrous,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.29, 30.</note> that but to remember them is an horrour; and ſo many, that but to repeat them might put a man out of breath. Yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they ſo monſtrous, nor ſo many, but that (without ſlandering our times and Nation) we may affirme, that too many Chriſtians (as they would be reputed) ſucceed the Gentiles in thoſe foule euils there mentioned by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, if not exceed them alſo. Notwithſtanding, ſee the gracious lenitie and mercie of our God in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16753:27"/>
correcting vs and our Land only with ſome bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and mildew, and ſome vnſeaſonable wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this our laſt harueſt: Whereas he might haue giuen vs ouer, as our neighbour countries, to conſume one another by inteſtine broiles and ciuill warres, or to haue beene deuoured and euen laid waſte by the ſword of a forreiner. Therefore as the Prophet ſpeakes to <hi>Niniueh, Art thou better than No,</hi> meaning <hi>Alexandria, which was full of people, that lay in the riuers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nahum 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>and had the waters round about it, whoſe ditch was the Sea, and her wall from the Sea:</hi> let me ſpeake to <hi>Great Britaine;</hi> Art thou better (I ſay not, fenced or enuironed, but, to Godward better affected) than <hi>Bohemia?</hi> or art thou leſſe ſinfull than <hi>France,</hi> or the <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate?</hi> or ſome other places alſo, in which haue beene acted ſo many wofull Tragedies of late, whiles thou neither fearing nor feeling the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of thoſe ruefull inhabitants, ſateſt as a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator, or a looker on? Are we better, I ſay? No; but God hath beene better vnto vs, if ſo be we are bettered by it, and at length haue learned by ſeeing our brethren beaten before vs, to feare our common Father, though we feele not his ſtripes: for bleſſed be the mightie God of our <hi>Iaakob,</hi> our Land ſtands yet vnſhaken in all theſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16753:28"/>
ſtormes, as a rocke in the midſt of the ſea, whiles the waters roare with tempeſts round about it. Indeed he hath of late ſmitten vs in ſome places, but (magnified be his mercy for euer) only with rods of men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.32.</note> not with men-rods, only with <hi>blaſting and mildew.</hi> And in ſtead of the noiſe of drums, and the clangour of the trumpets, and clattering of armour, and the fierce neighing of horſes, and the ſenſe-amazing terrour of the Cannon, we haue heard the ſound of bels cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs to Praier and Sermon. In other places they heare the ſhrikings of infants, their <hi>Rabels mourning for their children, and will not be comforted becauſe they are not:</hi> ours laugh and play in the ſtreets. For balls of wilde fire that burne vp others with their houſes, we haue felt but blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing winds in our fields: and for ſtreames of bloud which fat other lands with the gore of the inhabitants, we haue ſuffered but miſts and mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewes, that haue ſomewhat ſhrunke the fruits of our Land. O that we would be thankfull, he hath ſmitten vs only <hi>with blaſting and mildew.</hi> Yet neither had he thus corrected vs or this people in my text, if he had not beene prouoked by vs. But ſuch is the nature of ſinne, it angers the God of Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:16753:28"/>No wonder then (and let it be our next obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation) if it trouble and peruert the courſe of nature, by cauſing the Maker to turne kindly winds into blaſting, the mornings wholeſome moiſture into mildewes, and ſoft drops of raine into ſtones. God had no ſooner framed this world aboue and below as an excellent inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or paire of Organs to ſet forth his praiſe, and therein appointed man as the life and breath to ſound out his wiſdome and goodneſſe in and by all the creatures, but ſinne came in, and by the Serpents hiſſing marrd the muſicke: Then the heauens aboue began to looke diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly on the world below: Then the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments below perniciouſly to mutinie among themſelues, and all to conſpire mans diſſolution, whoſe matter was compounded of them. Then began the creatures ſome to rebell againſt him that reuolted from his Maker, and the reſt to doe him homage but <hi>with ſighes and groanes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.22.</note> Then the earth by enforcement of labour to yeeld her fruits to nouriſh him; but without labour, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of minerals, and herbes, and plants to poiſon him. Then his owne paſſions and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to fight againſt his reaſon, which ſhould haue beene regent ouer them. Then his owne
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16753:29"/>
humours to be at a perpetuall diſcord in him, till they had wrought his death. Then the father ſlew his poſteritie which were not yet borne. Then the brother imbrued his ſauage hands in the bloud of his brother. Then Nature turned vnnaturall; nor euer doe we heare of croſſes in and by the creature, till ſinne brought curſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world. This is it then that troubled Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; this is it which yet like <hi>Ahab</hi> troubles <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were our wiſdome then, to trouble it; if we loue our owne peace, not to be at peace with it, but continually to fight againſt it by true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. So ſhould the earth yeeld her kindly encreaſe, nor ſhould we need hereafter to feare or burning of her fruits by winds, or ſhrinking of them by vnwholeſome dewes. Would wee powre downe ſhowres of teares, how eaſily might we procure ſhowres of raine to quell ſuch windes, and to waſh away ſuch Mildewes, when they fall? But to complaine of our ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by theſe rods, or to bee querulous againſt theſe ſecond cauſes, and not to heed the hand of the chiefe mouer, what is it, but with thoſe foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh people in <hi>Aul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Gellius,</hi> to fight with the winde that dried vp their waters? or with vaine <hi>Xerxes</hi> in <hi>Herodotus</hi> to beat the <hi>Helleſpont</hi> that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16753:29"/>
broke downe his bridge. As in all other affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſo in theſe we muſt obſerue the ſupreme agent, God himſelfe, that ſends them for our good to profit by them: For at his command the windes blow and againe are huſht, the aire powres out raine or ſends downe Mildews vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth: and it reſts in his power to make our land yet more barren, if wee continue diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient; or to fructifie, if we repent. It is reported, that the riuer <hi>Nilus</hi> makes the land barraine if in ordinary places it either flow vnder fifteene cubits, or aboue ſeuenteene: and therefore that <hi>Preſter Iohn</hi> (through whoſe country it runneth, and in which it ariſeth from the hils called the <hi>Mountaines of the Moone</hi>) can at his pleaſure drowne a great part of <hi>Aegypt</hi> by letting out into the riuer certaine vaſt ponds and ſluces, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles of the melted ſnow from the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. Which that he may not doe, the <hi>Turkes</hi> who are now the Lords of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> pay a great tribute vnto him, as the Princes of that land haue done time out of minde: which tribute when the great <hi>Turke</hi> not long ſince denied to pay, till by experience he found this to be true, he was afterwards forced with a greater ſumme of money to renue his peace with that Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16753:30"/>
of the <hi>Abiſsines,</hi> and to continue his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient pay. The truth of this relation I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not: mine author is both of worth and credit eminent, and the thing it ſelfe credible. But this we all beleeue, that the great <hi>Emperour</hi> of heauen and earth, who ſits aboue vs, can at his pleaſure make our land and all the regions of the earth, fruitfull or barraine, by reſtraining or letting looſe the influences of his bleſſings from aboue. In reſpect whereof, beſides many other farre greater bonds of duty, we owe and ſhould pay vnto him a continuall tribute of thankfull obedience. This if we will not acknowledge and tender, he can force vs; for hee hath dams and ponds rather, an whole Ocean of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſtore, which he can (when it ſeemes him good) let downe vpon vs to make both the land fruitleſſe, and the ſoule it ſelfe accurſed that rebelleth. Not <hi>Blaſting</hi> onely, or <hi>Mildew,</hi> or fire, or haile, or lightning, or thunder, or vapours, or ſnow, or ſtormy windes, but euen whole vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and vollumes of curſes moe than can bee numbred, are preſt to doe his will, to afflict and vexe them that grieue his good ſpirit by their ſins and reuoltings eſpecially from the truth. Why then doe we taint the aire with rotten ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches?
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16753:30"/>
Why doe we with oathes and blaſphemies euen blaſt his heauens that can blaſt our earth? Why ſend we vp daily ſo many noyſome va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours of our ſinnes, againſt him that can ſend to vs ſo many wrathfull meſſengers of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure? They of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sydon</hi> ſhall riſe vp in iudgement againſt vs, to condemne vs of folly. They would not <hi>warre with Herod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 12.20.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe their countrey was nouriſhed by the Kings land:</hi> And ſhall wee by continuance in theſe and other ſinnes, dare the all-commanding Maieſtie that is aboue, by whoſe bleſſings the <hi>earth,</hi> heere below,<note place="margin">Eſay 55.10.</note> 
               <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth ſeed to the ſower, and bread to him that eateth? Doe we ſo reward the Lord, ô fooliſh people and vnwiſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.6.</note> 
               <hi>What are we ſtronger than he?</hi> or haue wee not read it, <hi>that none can deliuer out of his hands?</hi> For how ſhall any hand warre againſt him and preuaile, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom no hand can worke and proſper, as it followeth in the next circumſtance?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In all the labours of your hands] In all:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> The Manner.</note> It is an vniuerſall note, how ſhall wee take it? In the largeſt ſenſe; then it would include within the curſe, all their labours, whether of tillage or of trading, whether in their ſhips or ſhops, at home or abroad, in their houſes, or in their fields and vineyards. If all their labours of what
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16753:31"/>
kinde ſoeuer, none excepted, were vnderſtood, then their <hi>ſeeled houſes which they built,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hag. 1.3.</note> and all the workes of their mechanicall trades, ſhould haue beene ſubiect to <hi>Blaſting and Mildew,</hi> which were childiſh to thinke. Therefore not to extend this vniuerſall note any further than the Prophet heere reacheth it: this <hi>(All)</hi> hath a ſpeciall refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their workes of husbandry and tillage, in which a great part of this people had beene and were now conuerſant: for it is reported of <hi>Nebuzaradan,</hi> the king of <hi>Babels</hi> Steward, after the ſacking of <hi>Ieruſalem, that hee left of the poorer ſort of the people to dreſſe Vineyards,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 25.12.</note> 
               <hi>and to till the land.</hi> But what then? did the Lord onely correct Husbandmen? were not all the reſt of that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, though no tillers of ground, as much if not more to be blamed, for not building the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? for this was the principall cauſe why thus the Lord ſmote them: Yes, <hi>I ſmote you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in all the labours of your hands;</hi> hee meanes the whole people of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> for in that he curſed the labours of the plough, the curſe redounded to others of their workes alſo. If thoſe proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not, all other labours and Labourers fared the worſe for it.</p>
            <p>Whence firſt obſerue how much the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16753:31"/>
or miſerie of a people dependeth vpon the good or ill ſucceſſe of the ploughmans labours and other parts of husbandrie: for if God bleſſe not theſe, it is a correction vpon the whole Land and Countrey. Surely the noble hand of tillage is that which feeds the world, <hi>the King alſo</hi> (and he was the wiſeſt and greateſt King that ſaid it) <hi>conſiſteth by the field that is tilled.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.8.</note> Now if this hand that by Gods appointment reacheth meat to all mouthes, be diſcouraged, deſpiſed, and weakned, all other hands and hearts too muſt needs grow the fainter; for all are made of clay, and as their ſubſtance came from the earth, ſo muſt their ſuſtenance be taken thence, and how is that but ſpecially by tillage? Some wretched courſes of life, as the Vſurers, the Brokers, the Proiectors, the Monopoliſts,<note place="margin">Ioſua 6.9. Num. 11.25.</note> and the like <hi>gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hoſt of Dan,</hi> are as the ſpleene, the fuller and bigger their bags are, the leaner and lanker goes it with the Common-wealth: and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the leſſe ſuch fill and thriue, the fatter growes the body of the State. But the calling of the Husbandman is as the liuer; if it proſper, all fare the better for it; if it waſte, it proues <hi>Macies in corpore toto,</hi> a conſumption to the whole. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſtop the plough, is in Gods account to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16753:32"/>
ſtarue at leaſt the poore. Such then as decay both houſes and husbandrie, by <hi>ioyning houſe to houſe, and field to field, till there be no place for the poore, that ſo they may be placed by themſelues in the midſt of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 5.8.</note> are neither <hi>Caeſars</hi> friends, nor the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, no nor their owne: for <hi>this is in mine eares, ſaith the Lord of hoſts;</hi> this ſinne cries ſo high, that he doth not only heare it, but it is a continuall vexation vnto him, (as if it were ſome ringing in his eares that he would be rid of) or an inceſſant clamour that night and day impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately ſollicited iuſtice and called for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance:<note place="margin">Eſay 5.9.</note> 
               <hi>For this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhall their owne houſes one day be deſolate.</hi> Yea to ſuch (ſaith that Prophet) pertaines a <hi>Woe,</hi> and he cries it ſo loud, that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after him anſwers like an Eccho, <hi>Woe, for they couet an euill couetouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>and conſult ſhame to their owne houſes, whiles by deſtroying many people they make their poſſeſsions fields of bloud,</hi> purchaſed in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with the hazard of the liues of Gods inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for want of food: for how can they be but enemies to the liues of many, that hinder thoſe labours which ſhould feed all? and which when God ſmiteth, he would haue it noted as a corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction on the whole Nation, though the curſe fall immediatly but vpon the works of the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16753:32"/>
as here, <hi>I ſmote you in all the labours of your hands,</hi> and yet all theſe labours (to ſpeake properly) were but the labours of the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Which againe thus offereth another leſſon to vs:</p>
            <p>That the ſinnes of a whole Land or people are ſometimes corrected but in ſome one or another calling or trade of life, by not bleſſing which the Lord yet would chaſten all. The neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of building the Temple was generally the fault of all, of the Prieſt as of the people, of the Gouernours as of the common ſort, of Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as of Ploughmen; yet as if the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had beene more negligent than all the reſt, (which is more than can be proued) his labours are ſmitten for all the reſt, and in them all are ſmitten. As when the whole body is ſicke, the Surgeon labours to cure it, by opening a veine in ſome one part or other, by which hee doth abate the rankeneſſe of the humours in all the reſt: ſo to medicine a ſinfull ſtate or people, ſometimes the Lord ſmites them in the hand of husbandry,<note place="margin">Hag. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>When it ſowes much and brings but in a little:</hi> ſometimes he lets them bloud in the arme of the ſouldiery,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.43.</note> 
               <hi>When he goes not forth with their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to battell, but takes away the edge of their ſword:</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:16753:33"/>
ſometimes in one calling, ſometimes in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſometimes at once in a many: yet all is but as <hi>phlebotomie,</hi> or letting of bloud in ſome parts, to eaſe the whole of that ſuperfluity of vices that would deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>If then the Lord at this time hath made, not <hi>our Vine dreſſers to howle,</hi> for wee may ſay of our land, as the Poet doth of <hi>Aegypt, Terraſuis conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta bonis,</hi> and it hath no ſuch neede of theſe: but if he hath made our <hi>Husbandmen aſhamed becauſe of the harueſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioel 1.11.</note> if our Clothiers to mourne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the wooll and the flaxe; if the poore to crie (murmure they ſhould not) that haue mouthes and no meat, hands and no worke, which (God bee mercifull to our nation) is a double miſerie; thinke thus with our ſelues, all ſorts haue ſinned as well as theſe: <hi>For wee fall away more and more. The whole body is ſicke,</hi> though the phyſicke be applied to ſome parts. Yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this but an argument of Gods mercy, who as a ſhepherd, ſends his barking dogs of dearth and pouerty after vs his wandring ſheepe, not to deuoure vs, but to reduce vs to his fold, and to keepe vs within the compaſſe of obedience to his lawes. Surely hee meanes our good in all this: for as a man ſuffereth thoſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16753:33"/>
beaſts which he appointeth ſhortly to be ſlaine, to goe in his deepeſt paſtures and to breake his hedges without reſtraint, to the end they may be ſooner fatted for the ſhambles, but keepes ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch as he purpoſeth to keepe aliue; ſo dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Lord with vs: in that by theſe correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he now abridgeth our land of that fulneſſe which we our ſelues deſire, and ſuffers vs not to tranſgreſſe his ſtatutes without controlement, it is to preſerue vs: did either hee intend our ſlaughter, we ſhould (it may be) not want a richer feeding: or would wee amend our liues, we ſhould not lacke it, might it be good for vs. But hee knowes that <hi>fulneſſe of bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 16.49.</note> through mans corruption cauſeth much filthineſſe. This if our former plenty haue brought forth, hee purpoſeth in mercy to purge vs, and to make vs fit for better bleſſings; of which we cannot be capable till he hath emptied our ſoules of their naturall defiledneſſe, and cleanſed them by toſſing vs vp and downe in ſome waters of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. Your ſelues will haue your cups and glaſſes ſcowred ſometimes in ſalt, into which you powre your wine or oyle, but care not to haue the troughs waſhed, in which are ſerued your dogs or ſwine. Touching ſuch as <hi>with the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16753:34"/>
dog returne to his vomit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>and with the ſwine that was waſhed to her wallowing in the mire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 22.11.</note> is that ſaid, <hi>Hee that is filthy let him be filthy;</hi> but thus he ſpeaketh to them whom he hath appointed to be veſſels of glory;<note place="margin">Eſay 1.</note> 
               <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy.</hi> And againe, <hi>Waſh ye, make ye cleane;</hi> and if at his perſwaſion they will not waſh themſelues by repentance in teares, he will make them doe it by troubles; for it is a worke which hee will haue done, to which while his people doe not cheerefully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate their hands, he can curſe them in other labours of their hands, as here, <hi>I ſmote you in all the labours of your hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In all]</hi> Theſe <hi>all,</hi> are properly but all the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of the Husbandman (as hath beene ſaid) yet becauſe all ſmarted whiles but theſe were ſmitten, he ſpeakes it indefinitely to all, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding any, <hi>I ſmote you in all the labours of your hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which in the third place lights another can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to let vs ſee how we ought to <hi>ſympathiſe</hi> one with another, in thoſe ſeuerall afflictions that befall vs. I would vtter it in this propoſition: The croſſes that befall others in their lawfull callings, doing their honeſt endeuours, wee ſhould eſteeme partly our owne, according to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16753:34"/>
that rule of the Apoſtle;<note place="margin">Gal. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>Beare yee one anothers burden, and ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt.</hi> So he ſpeakes, as if compaſſion were the fulneſſe and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the law: and indeed ſo it is,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.8. Gal. 5.14.</note> For <hi>loue is the fulfilling of the law.</hi> Theſe places are Scripture enough for proofe: may it pleaſe you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the reaſon of the duty thus; A Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth is called a body, ſundry callings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men therein, are as parts organicall, or members of the ſame: There is an head of gouernment that rules all; an eie of counſell that ſees for all; a tongue of vtterance that ſpeakes for all; armes of valour that fight for all; hands of labour that worke for all. Some callings are the leggs which ſupport the reſt; as the Clothi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and others which are conuerſant about the ſtaple commodities of the land; others as feet of traffique for commutation to tranſport the reſt. Now all theſe as fellow members ſhould worke for the good of all, and ſhould be ſo combined in affection, that the hurting or weakening of any one, ſhould make the reſt ſenſible of hurt done to them. For inſtance; If but the labours oft he Husbandman be blaſted, all ſhould feele it, as if themſelues were ſmitten. If Merchandiſe and Merchants Ships that plough the ſea for vs
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16753:35"/>
to bring in riches, and are the walls of an Iland, be diſcouraged by Pyrats, and tempeſts, or any other ſad diſaſters at Sea or Land: If Clothiers and clothing, the ancient honour and rich com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of our Nation goe downe, all other Trades and men of other callings ſhould haue a fellow feeling of thoſe miſeries: yea all ſhould pittie, all ſhould endeuour a redreſſe, or pray for it; the Prince as the Peſant, the Iudge on the Bench, as the Priſoner at the Barre; he that hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Pike, as hee that handleth the Pen; the night-ſtudent, as the day-labourer; for the whole body cannot be perfectly whole, if any part be wounded. And therefore, <hi>if one member ſuffer, all ſhould ſuffer with it.</hi> But if in ſtead of commiſeration and compaſſion one towards another in our ſeuerall callings, there be nothing but repining againſt, and vndermining of one another: If the Tenant enuy his Landlord, and the Landlord ſet ſuch rents on his grounds, that the Tenant cannot liue with comfort: If the Leuite fret at the Lawyers fulneſſe, and the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer grudge at the Leuites portion, which is Gods by his owne claime: If moſt maligne the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, and the begging Courtier would ſquiſe all as ſpunges: If moſt abhor the Souldier, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16753:35"/>
the bloudy Souldier deſire to prey vpon all as a <hi>Vultur</hi> on dead carkaſſes: If ſome would haue peace, to oppreſſe the poore, and others would haue war, to rob the rich: If ſome would haue the ſeas open to returne vs forraine vanities, for the neceſſaries of the land; and others pray for times of repriſall, againe to be fiſhing in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled waters, (though goods ſo gotten at ſea, and God knowes how, haue ſtrangely melted in the hands of many ſince they landed) If thus one ſort <hi>bite and deuoure another, let vs take heed</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>leſt we be deuoured one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Fourthly, take notice hence of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction;</p>
            <p>That when God bleſſeth not, no labour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpereth, how honeſt or commodious ſoeuer the calling be wherein we labour. A more lawfull calling than that of tillage can be none: It had <hi>God</hi> for the firſt Author,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.19. Gen. 3.23. Gen. 9.20.</note> and <hi>Adam</hi> the ſole heire of the world for the firſt Practitioner. <hi>Noah</hi> the Patriarch that ſuruiued the old world, liued to till the new alſo;<note place="margin">Gen. 26.12.</note> and <hi>Iſaack</hi> a type of Chriſt tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Husbandman. <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet was a Ploughman,<note place="margin">1 Kings 19.19.</note> and the greateſt Kings haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted both in the praiſe of it, as <hi>Solomon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.8.</note> and in the practiſe of it, as <hi>Vzziah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chr. 26.10.</note> And that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16753:36"/>
ſhould not be aſhamed to learne the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of it, the Lord (who is greater than all) is ſaid to teach it, for thus the Prophet of the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,<note place="margin">Eſay. 28.26.</note> 
               <hi>His God inſtructeth him.</hi> Chriſt yet the more to grace it,<note place="margin">Iohn 15.1:</note> hath called his Father an <hi>Husbandman,</hi> his Church a <hi>field,</hi> his Miniſters <hi>labourers</hi> in it; mans heart reformed, <hi>Gods husbandrie;</hi> his owne word, <hi>the ſeed;</hi> good works, <hi>the fruits,</hi> Angels the <hi>reapers,</hi> and the generall iudgement <hi>the Lords great harueſt.</hi> Nor is it more honeſt than vſefull, for <hi>the abundance of the earth is ouer all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.8.</note> that is, there is no worldly thing comparable to the reuenues of the earth, whether we reſpect the vniuerſalitie of their vſe, in that all euen from the King to the kitchin boy are fed by them; or the excellencie thereof, in that they nouriſh life, which gold and ſiluer cannot doe. The earth as an Oliue berrie hath our food without, not within; her mines and metals are too hard for our digeſtion, nor need we to digge into her wombe for meat; if we doe but ſearch her out-ſides, or draw fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes in her ſurface, we ſhall finde ſtore of moſt precious and vſefull riches. This, <hi>Aeſope,</hi> or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe he was, ſweetly conueyed to our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in that parable of the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who when he died, told his ſonnes that he
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16753:36"/>
had left vnto them gold, buried but a little vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ground in his vineyard: which they digged all ouer after his death, but gold they found none; yet by ſtirring the mould about the roots of their Vines, the next yeeres vintage proued ſo plentifull, as made good the old mans promiſe in effect, according to the ſenſe, not the ſound of his words. So that whether wee conſider the honeſty or the vſe of it, this calling for worldly things hath no fellow: Yet as honeſt, as vſefull as it is, when God is not pleaſed to bleſſe the endeuours of it, they cannot proſper. <hi>To build an houſe, or to watch a citie,</hi> are both lawfull enough; and to be ſedulous and vigilant in theſe workes, is euen laudable: yet if Gods fauour be not preſent to <hi>worke</hi> in the one, and to <hi>watch for the other,</hi> the Pſalmiſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 127.2.</note> 
               <hi>that both theſe are in vaine. It is not earely riſing, or going late to bed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10.22.</note> 
               <hi>but the bleſsing of God that maketh rich:</hi> And this hath <hi>quandam vniuerſalem influentiam in omnia opera bona,</hi> an vniuerſall influence into all good endeuours, which when God will reſtraine, in vaine man wearieth himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Be this then euer in our memorie, in all our workes, begunne, continued, and ended in him, ſtill to depend on his goodneſſe, and ſo to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16753:37"/>
his name: For as without the influence of his bleſſing, no labour of ours can make vs thriue; ſo with it and by it all our lawfull works ſhall proſper, though the world and malice it ſelfe ſhould be ſet to croſſe vs. When an Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>London</hi> was giuen to vnderſtand by a Courtier, that Queene <hi>Mary</hi> in her diſpleaſure againſt the city, threatned thence to diuert both Terme and Parliament to <hi>Oxford;</hi> hee asked of him the queſtion, whether ſhe would turne thither the Channell of the Thames or no; if not, ſaid he, by the grace of God we ſhall doe well enough. When either enuy of meaner men repineth, or the anger of greater perſons rageth againſt our thriuing, wee ſhall doe well to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that there is <hi>a riuer whoſe ſtreames ſhall make glad the city of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 46.4.</note> a current (I meane) of Gods bleſſings, which while he vouchſafeth to our honeſt labours and lawfull callings, no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of man or deuill ſhall euer be able to ſtop or auert. So whiles this riuer of God keepes its courſe, we ſhall doe well enough: but if his hand for our ſinnes turne it aſide (as it were) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another channell, no wonder then if wee proſper not in <hi>all the labours of our hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, hence obſerue, that it is a iuſt thing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16753:37"/>
with God not to bleſſe them in their workes, that neglect his worke. The point riſeth thus: The building of the Temple was Gods worke (for this he had enioyned them) but the tilling of their grounds, and dreſſing of their Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards were their workes: They were negligent to doe the former, therefore God curſt them in the latter: <hi>I ſmote you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in all the labours of your hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To omit other proofe of a doctrine ſo plaine, euen that of the Prophet ſhall now ſerue the turne,<note place="margin">Ier. 48.10.</note> 
               <hi>Curſed is he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently.</hi> Hence inferre this concluſion; If the not builders of the Temple bee accurſed, how ſhall the pullers of it downe looke for a bleſſing?</p>
            <p>But what is this to vs? we pull it not downe. True: yet if we be not builders of it, we are as culpable as theſe <hi>Iewes.</hi> Yea but wee haue no Churches to build: be it ſo; yet the Lord hath a worke for euery one of vs; yea, a Temple which yet muſt be built by vs, or wee are accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. What is that? <hi>S. Ierome</hi> vpon this place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes vs;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.11.</note> It is <hi>to build vp our ſelues a Temple vnto God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.</note> 
               <hi>vpon Chriſt Ieſus the foundation and the Corner Stone;</hi> according to that of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Iude 20.v.</note> 
               <hi>Edifie
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16753:38"/>
your ſelues in your moſt holy faith.</hi> Yea the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> tels vs what this Temple is,<note place="margin">Ierem. 7.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Truſt not in lying words, ſaying the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord: The Temple of the Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are theſe</hi> (as it is in the laſt tranſlation:) what are thoſe? It followeth in the fift verſe, <hi>To redreſſe our waies and our workes, to execute iudgement betweene man and man; not to oppreſſe the ſtranger, or the fatherleſſe, or the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; to ſhed no innocent bloud, nor to walke after other Gods, &amp;c. For this is the will,</hi> yea and the worke <hi>of God</hi> too,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>Euen our ſanctification,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.3.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.17.</note>Againe, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells vs what it is; <hi>The Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God is holy, which ye are,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. So then we our ſelues are this Temple, which <hi>muſt bee built in faith, Iude verſe</hi> 20. and <hi>renewed in knowledge, Col.</hi> 3.10. and <hi>reedified by loue,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1. and repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by repentance: for thus ſaith the Lord; <hi>The heauen is my Throne, and the earth is my footſtoole, where is that houſe that ye will build vnto me, and where is that place of my reſt, Eſay</hi> 66.1. He anſwers in the next verſe, <hi>To him will I looke euen to him that is poore and of a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my words.</hi> This then is the ſpirituall Temple of the Lord, the new man is the new Temple;<note place="margin">Pſal. 132.14.</note> 
               <hi>This is his reſt for euer, heere will he dwell, for hee hath a delight therein.</hi> The <hi>Babylonians</hi> defaced the firſt materiall Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16753:38"/>
and the <hi>Iewes</hi> were charged to build it againe, which while they neglected to doe, God <hi>ſmote them in all their labours.</hi> The ghoſtly enemie of our ſoules, through enuie and malice hath razed and demoliſht in vs that goodly frame of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, in which we were created at firſt, <hi>after Gods owne image, in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe.</hi> Now this the mercifull God would, ſhould be built againe, and thus calls vpon vs to doe it: <hi>Be renewed in the ſpirit of your minde, Epheſ.</hi> 4.23. and <hi>Put on the new man which is renewed in knowledge, after the Image of him that created him, Col.</hi> 3.10. This is his worke, and if we make it not ours alſo, that is,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>By working out our owne ſaluation with feare and trembling,</hi> how iuſtly may the Lord curſe vs in all our labours, as he did this people? Either then let vs attend Gods <hi>husbandrie, Gods building,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.9.</note> that is, the reformation of our ſelues and others, or looke not that hee ſhould proſper our Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, or whatſoeuer labour elſe is ours. In vaine ſhall we purpoſe to preuent Blaſting and Mildew by early ſowing, if we repent too late. If we will not <hi>plough vp</hi> our hearts with a godly ſorrow, that the ſeed of his <hi>word may take root;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>and bring forth fruit,</hi> he can make our ſeed-to rot vnder the clods, or by corrections moe than
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16753:39"/>
we can imagine, ſmite it in its growth, and euen fruſtrate our faireſt hopes, be we neuer ſo skilfull in chuſing of the ſoile to ſowe in, or in obſeruing of the ſeaſon. If we would that our earthly affaires ſhould proue ſuccesfull, our greateſt care ſhould be, firſt, <hi>to ſeeke the kingdome of God,</hi> and to recouer that by Chriſt which we loſt in <hi>Adam.</hi> A Perſian King (were it <hi>Darius Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſpis,</hi> or <hi>Xerxes,</hi> it is not certaine) when the Grecians had taken from him <hi>Sardi</hi> a famous ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe, in Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> time one of the ſeuen Churches, charged that euery day at din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, one ſpeaking aloud ſhould remember him, that the Grecians had taken the citie <hi>Sardi</hi> from him. Beloued, wee haue loſt more than a citie: we haue loſt our ſoules, which are of more worth than all the world beſides, if Chriſt doe not reſcue them from the hands of Satan. O then that we would giue <hi>our Redeemer no reſt</hi> by inceſſant praiers, till he deliuer vs, and <hi>repaire our ruines.</hi> O that ſtill we would bee calling vpon him to remember his loſſe and ours, (for ours is his) till we haue regained by him, that which at firſt was taken from vs by the enemie, euen the Image of our God after which wee were created. This is the Temple of the Lord,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16753:39"/>
and how ſhould we mourne in our ſoules, and giue the <hi>temples of our head no reſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 132.5.</note> 
               <hi>till we haue found out</hi> in our ſelues a place for this Temple of the Lord, that we may be a ſpirituall habitation for the mighty God of <hi>Iaakob?</hi> Yea this ſhould bee our care ſtill, by repentance to reedifie the ruines of our ſoules; in which worke alone to thriue were euen felicitie enough, though we did not proſper in any worldly labour. But alas, too many of vs haue too great a part in the ſecond generall part of my text, which may ſpeake to vs as to this people;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Generall Part.</note> 
               <hi>Yet yee haue not returned to me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Loſe not the fruit of your patience (I beſeech you) in the laſt act: and touching this I ſhall haue done in a word; for heere I ſhall but point at ſome few ſuch things as might hence be noted, and leaue them to be enlarged and applied by your owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations.</p>
            <p>As firſt, the goodneſſe of God in his correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of vs, that he intends them to be but dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and inſtructions, to teach vs how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto him, for that was the end here where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſmote this people, that they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne; and it is his aime in all thoſe afflictions which he ſends and we ſuffer, for all ſuch <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:16753:40"/>
are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch nocuments are documents to them whom he chaſtens in loue.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ilneſſe of man in his corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that he is a runnagate from his God, and euen then vnwilling to be reuoked from his wanderings, when God yet layes ſuch croſſes in his way, that if he returne not, he cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the inefficacie or inſufficiencie of afflictions, which of themſelues are neuer able to reduce vs to our Fathers home, if they be not ſanctified to vs, or we rather vnto them. Thus wee finde it in the parable of the Prodigall, that it was not ſo much the ſenſe of his owne miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as the confidence he had in his fathers mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, which made him returne with this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>I will goe to my father.</hi> If as he had ſpent his portion, he had alſo loſt the comfortable aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his fathers loue and relenting good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to re-accept him, he had ſtill wallowed in his ſins, and ſtaied by the trough with his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane fellow-feeders: for afflictions of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are of a deſtroying nature; as coraſiues they eat, but they cure not; and therefore corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions if they be miniſtred vnto vs not corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, not ſanctified to vs by grace, of themſelues
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16753:40"/>
(as poiſons) may doe hurt, but can profit vs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to conuerſion. <hi>O Lord, thou haſt ſmitten them</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>but they haue not returned vnto thee.</hi> In all our afflictions then, let this euermore be our praier, that we may profit by them, leſt it may be ſaid to vs, as <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> ſpeakes of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who were not bettered by their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; <hi>Perdidiſtis vtilitatem calamitatis, &amp; miſerrimi facti estis, &amp; peſsimi permanſiſtis:</hi> Calamities haue done you no good; ye haue beene afflicted, and yet are as ill affected as euer. When phyſicke works not with the Patient, what comfort? When croſſes teach not, what hope? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (good Lord) mingle thy grace with thy rods, that they may driue vs home to thee, whoſe armes of mercy are euer open to receiue the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent; That ſo ſuffering with our Sauiour, we may reigne with him, and come at length to that kingdome of reſt, where thou wilt <hi>wipe away all teares</hi> and feares from our eyes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
